This CodeWorld task is about a loading screen.
Here we have some definitions given where we
have to replace the undefined parts again.
We have a 'loading' function, and we have a
'circles' function and a 'partialCircle' function.
The 'circles' function is used by the
'loading' function, and the 'partialCircle'
function shall be used by this 'circles' function.
There is again a preview of how the result
should look, and we can view it here.
It's a loading screen with rotating part circles
and they have different rotation directions and
gaps in between them.
These gaps are important, so
we shall create circles where
the gaps are on opposing sides.
And they have different sizes.
We shall use the 'partialCircle'
function in order to draw circles.
Especially, it is given what the
parameters of a partial circle are
and here it says that it takes a five-tuple of the
animation and the animation time as parameters.
So first of all, we have this five-tuple, and then
we have let's say t again for the animation time.
And the five-tuple consists of radius, thickness,
gap size, the speed of rotation,
and the color of the circle.
Let's name these parameters first. So we have
- the radius -
- the thickness -
- gap -
- speed -
and the color.
Now we shall define such a partial circle.
What is a partial circle?
A partial circle is an arc.
And if we look into the
documentation, we find args here.
There are other parts of circle types
or part circle types, like sector
which is a solid sector of a circle which
is a pie slice - which is not what we want!
But here are thick arcs as well.
Thick arcs are arcs, and those are the
parameters that we need to remember.
So it's a line width, starting,
and ending angle, and the radius.
When we want to draw a partial
circle, we need these parameters.
I have said we take the 'thickArc'
function, because then we can define
the variety of the thickness of the arc.
And the first parameter is indeed the
thickness, then we have some begin and end,
- I just write it down here so that we are
reminded that we have some begin and end. -
And we have a radius.
We need to figure out what
begin is and what end is.
Begin and end, those are some parts of a circle.
In fact, we know that the gap is some space
between or defines that it's some space between
the circle parts.
Begin and end are angles! When we think
about this we can say we want to have the
size of the arc growing with
different definitions for gap.
So begin and end shall somehow depend on gap.
When we look at the gap parameter, which is
probably also the one we - well, it's the
third parameter here, I would assume we just
take the same parameter here within circles
because it's somehow intuitive to use the same
parameter for circles and partial circles.
So when we have the gap given - so this
is this part here - this is the gap.
When we look at the animation
we can somehow figure out.
So this is some part of the
circle which is - maybe a
tenths of the circle or something
like this in size of the gap.
Or maybe an eighth or something like this, and this
is the biggest gap we have - with four and a half.
Well, the widest gap we could have
would be if we have no circle at all.
And which would in return mean that we
have an angle of 0 and 180 degrees.
I think it's more intuitive to just define one
angle and have the other as the negate of it.
It would be in that case 90
degrees and minus 90 degrees.
I say 'end' is the negate of 'begin', so if
'begin' is 90 degrees then 'end' is minus 90.
And 90 degrees would be half of pi
- so this is 90 degrees in radians,
because we are in radians we
have to think of this part.
Then we have "minus gap", and now we have
to consider again that this four and a half
this one shall not be greater than half of pi.
So I just assume it's a tenth of this size maybe
what we can consider as the size of the gap.
So it would be 0.45 which we subtract from pi.
So again: when we have the biggest
gap - this one - we would have.
The biggest gap is um half of pi which
is 90 degrees, and then we subtract...
No again! This would be a full circle
and this would mean a gap of zero if we
have the full circle, and if we subtract for the
whole gap, this basically would end up at zero.
And now we have this partial circle, but now we
could not see anything if we run this program.
In fact, I think it should
crash - somehow - and it does,
because we have undefined within these circles.
Now - how can we see our
partial circles actually?
We can use list comprehension here because
we could get a parameter for circles which
is the list of all the definitions here.
We can use this one here - this is the circles -
well, let's call it circs - so this is the circles.
And we have a time parameter
and then we can say - well, we use our
function 'pictures' which is defined here.
Just as a reminder, we have
the 'pictures' function defined
within CodeWorld which takes a list
of pictures and returns a picture.
We can use this one here as well - so pictures!
And then we use list comprehension to extract all
the parameter definitions and give them to partial
circle where we can then draw the parts
of the circle - its partial circle!
What do we give to the partial circle?
We give a part and the time, and the
part we get from the list of circles.
So that's the list of circles
and we get the partial circles!
Now we can apply this and we
shall see something, I hope!
Yes! We see that we have some
circle parts drawn here which are
not colored yet - we shall color
them in order to get this picture.
Let's do this by using the 'colored' function.
We have the color defined here, so we
can use 'colored' - and the color and
because this is a parameter here -
we get whenever the 'partialCircle'
function is called - and this is defined
here - so we apply the actual color!
We saw that when we draw this circle it draws
actually just half of the circle. Right?
We draw some part here, and we draw some part
here, and we see there's something missing already
but we need the other side as well!
And within the previous task, I have defined a
'mirrored' function - this would suit well here.
This 'mirrored' function was based on
reflected, and we have reflected defined here.
Here we can see - reflected is a picture reflected
across a line through the origin at this angle.
So when we want to use reflected, we can
simply apply this here - so reflected.
It takes an angle and the picture
which shall be reflected - in this case
we want to reflect it across the y-axis.
That's why we rotate the reflecting
axis by 90 degrees using pi and a half.
I guess if we would just use reflected
with zero we would see nothing - I guess.
Let's try it out first!
Reflected with zero - it's nothing changed
because we are reflecting this part of the
circle to that part and that part of the
circle to the other part, so nothing happens.
But if we use
the half of pi, then we reflect across the
y-axis and then we see it's on the other side.
But again I said we want to
use reflected in order to get
the other part as well, and this we
did the last time by defining mirrored.
And mirrored was just the reflected part.
So mirror takes an angle and a picture
and it's the reflected part by angle
reflected part and the picture itself.
If we define it like this and use
mirrored here instead of reflected, then
we shall get both parts of these circles.
Which is in fact happening here.
Now we define the type for mirrored as well.
mirrored is of type double to picture to picture.
We shall always define the types for
functions because it's better code style:
we actually see what the
'mirrored' function does.
Well, we have these parameters here,
but it's better to define the types
this function is actually using.
And in fact, we have the pictures
second parameter and the angle as first.
We apply this 'mirrored' function here in
order to get both parts of the circle.
And now we have to rotate our circle.
Important is here - for our circle's important is
that, when we rotate the circle or part circle,
we have to rotate the whole thing.
So we have to rotate the complete part.
Well, we could actually
rotate the mirrored part here,
but we shall not just rotate this part here.
Because this will not work well with
the mirror part, because this defines
the half circle or the part circle, and
the other part circle, and keeps the gaps.
And if we just rotate the inner
part, we will get a weird result.
We rotate by rotated - by using rotated.
And we have a speed which is given. Which we
of course have to multiply with t in
order to get a result of moving circles.
And if we apply this, then we get something
- which could actually - which looks actually
like the picture we've got
before or which we shall create.
And I just want to show you
that when we do this here.
So when rotated is within the mirrored part,
then I think we should get something weird.
Yes, this is not what we want!
So - again I undo what I did.
We have the rotated part on the outside
and rotate the whole thing in order to get
the animation that we want to have. Okay!
The task says we can modify our
animations a bit in order to get
different animations like this one or this one.
I show you these animations:
so this is one of those
so there's some white part moving in the
counter direction - which will look like this.
You can see it like I do - so we have
these rotating part circles,
but there's also a gap moving.
And then we have this part here where
also a gap is moving on the outside and
this gap is actually running
faster than the other gap.
If you would like to say it like this.
And how can we implement
this within the animations?
We can actually define just other part
circles here within our 'loading' function.
So this is a modification of the program, so
when you handed it in you probably had a comment
for the other definition of the task.
We do not have now to do - but
we can modify the program here
within CodeWorld because there
is no checking of the template.
And in the first part, I just tried to modify
the inner circle part - which is roughly
a circle - which is like the black
circle except for two things.
So I want to draw a white circle - a
part circle - above the black circle
which rotates in the other direction.
So the speed of rotation is the third parameter
and we want to rotate in the opposite direction.
So there is some minus we
have to do for the rotation.
And also, we want to have the value which is
for the angle - which is the
opposite of this angle here - right?
So here's pi and a half minus
gap divided by 10. And this is
the begin, and we have to figure out
how to define the opposite of this so.
If we assume we had 1.5 written here, how ...
No! I want to have the
opposite of this angle here.
When I apply
a 0 here, I would - in the second
one I would get - pi and a half.
I would have here something
which is the opposite.
So we should have something which is
five times pi. So five times pi then
would be the opposite - minus the gap
- that's what we want to have here!
So maybe write this as a little helper.
And the opposite - which is the opposite angle -
the opposite angle of what we want to
draw is 5 times pi and then minus x.
So here we want to have the opposite
the other part of the angle.
Which should result in the
same size of the gap as before
and if we apply this let's see what's happening.
We see something - but not very
good - because: What's happening?
Well - we have the wrong color defined
uh this one shall be white and not black.
And if we apply this one with white
then we see there's a moving gap -
and it does not look perfect yet.
But we can fix this by increasing the size of
the - or the thickness of the circle. Right?
So if we increase the thickness then
the part is covered completely and now
we have this part of the animation
which should roughly look like here. Right?
So we have something moving
in the opposite direction.
And now to add the same - we can add
the same trick for the other part.
Which is the outer circle
which is - this one here.
I duplicate this part as well and now
we think about what's happening here.
Again we want to have a white circle
part moving above the other one.
This time we want to move it in the
same direction, but it shall be faster.
Yes, if we look here.
One part here is faster than the other one.
Let's just say one maybe and
again we increase the size
of - or the thickness of the circle in
order to cover the other circle part.
So now we have something which
looks maybe roughly like this.
Well, what did I forget here?
It's the opposite we want to have. And maybe I
should increase the size of the circle a little
bit more because that still sometimes some
parts of the other circle are visible.
So let's have a look at this one now.
We want to have the opposite of these
for 4.5 because we want to just have
the part drawn - we want
to have a circle which is
as big as the gap; that's why we take
the opposite function here again.
And now have a look again at this one.
Maybe you can see that the actual speed of the
rotations - is not that - within the inner circle,
that the rotation in the right direction of the
gaps is not the same as in the left direction - so
the rotation in the left direction is a bit
faster than the rotation in the right direction.
So you can actually recover from that
by reducing the speed of the white
part and then you get something
which should look similar.
And you could draw more circles by
defining them here and so on and so forth.
But as we considered within this task, I think we
have covered it quite well by using the arcs here.
If you want to see a different definition on how
to solve this task or a different
version on how to solve this task,
you can have a look at the German version of this
task because there you find a different way of
defining the gaps within these circles and
there's a different approach to solving this task.